<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Character of a rebellion, and what England may expect from one, or, The designs of dissenters examined by reason, experience, and the laws and statutes of the realm</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53091</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N91</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4252</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12968953</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12968953</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96141</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53091)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96141)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 393:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Character of a rebellion, and what England may expect from one, or, The designs of dissenters examined by reason, experience, and the laws and statutes of the realm</title>
                  <author>Nalson, John, 1638?-1686.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Benj. Tooke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A royalist tract describing chaos brought about by a rebellion inspired by dissenters; one result would be the "discharter" of Virginia, Maryland, Carolina, etc., royal grants.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Nalson by Wing. DNB does not mention this in its account of John Nalson, 1638?-1686, a royalist pamphleteer. Other authorities list this under title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Colonies --  America.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96141:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96141:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CHARACTER OF A REBELLION, And what ENGLAND May expect from one.</p>
            <p>OR, <hi>The Deſigns of Diſſenters</hi> Examined by REASON, EXPERIENCE, And the LAWS and STATUTES OF THE REALM.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Benj. Tooke,</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:96141:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96141:2"/>
            <head>The CHARACTER of a REBELLION, AND What <hi>England</hi> may expect from one, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HE does not deſerve the name of an <hi>Engliſhman,</hi> who in a time of Common and Imminent Danger, dare not ſtand up for his King, his Religion, his Country, Laws, Liberty, and the moſt Excellent Conſtitution of Government in the whole World. And that all theſe are in the moſt apparent hazard even from thoſe People who pretend to be the great Oppoſers of Popery and Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Government, I appeal not only to the Swarms of Inſolent, Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous, Seditious and Malitious Pamphlets which of late have made the Preſs and the whole Nation groan, and are one of the greateſt Grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Peſts of the Commonwealth, but to that general fear which the Inſolence of Factious Diſſenters hath raiſed, and thereby given too juſt ground for apprehenſions of their breaking out into Rebellion and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrections.</p>
            <p>I am ſatisfied that they lay a great ſtreſs upon the Policy of this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, to incourage their Party and frighten their Oppoſers, by the frequent boaſts of their Strength, Numbers, and what may follow if they be not gratified; how dangerous it is to diſoblige them; and I believe they had much rather compaſs their Deſigns by theſe artifices, than run the Chance and Riſque of a Deciſion by the Sword; and I know alſo, that many of the principal Engineers have more of the Fox than of the Lion, and are better at the Encounters of the Tongue and Pen, than of the glittering Steel; but yet I think no Enemy ought to be Eſteemed contemptible, and the very firſt Eſſayes towards Rebellion ought to be encountered; it being not impoſſible but Law and Reaſon may baffle and ſubdue them, before they take the Field; and it will be a very happy Combat where nothing is ſpilt but Ink.</p>
            <p>It cannot diſcourage me, that of late ſome Mercenary Pens and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning Perſons have countenanced the notorious Enemies of the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht Government with the Character of the only true Proteſtants, and that Libelling has been eſteemed a Virtue, if not a part of their Religion; Lying and Defamation the ſcandals of good Moral Heathens, have been adopted into Chriſtianity; while, ſuch as durſt adventure to aſſert, or appear in defence of, the Government and known Laws, were loaded with all the invidious Reproaches of <hi>Billingsgate</hi> Invention; and moſt certainly with the name of <hi>Papiſt.</hi> I have a Veneration for men of Senſe, but cannot but deſpiſe thoſe little writing Things who are but one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree advanced above Apes and Monkeys that chatter and bite as they are ſet on. And certainly a more contemptible piece of Senceleſs De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction was hardly ever invented on this ſide Bedlam, than to affirm
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96141:3"/>that the Papiſts are contriving to ſubvert the Government, and pretend to be Zealous againſt them, as all honeſt men are againſt whoever ſhall attempt that, and at the ſame time, to brand all ſuch as vigorouſly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear for it againſt both Papiſts and Phanatiques, with the title of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Polititians move great Wheels by little ones, and the King and Government muſt be diſarmed, by this Popular Odium, of all their true Friends under the Notion of Papiſts, that ſo they may come under the Guardianſhip and Protection of theſe true Proteſtant Diſſenters; and is it poſſible to Conjecture they would not then be in good hands? I may be miſtaken, but I believe I am not ſingle in my Opinion, that they would be in <hi>Salva Cuſtodia,</hi> according to the Engliſh of Jaylors.</p>
            <p>And after all the repeated Affronts both to his Sacred Majeſty and Perſons of the moſt Eminent Characters and Loyalty in the Nation, they muſt not be reproved or cenſured for fear of diſ-uniting Proteſtants, or forcing them to Rebel. But truly if they proceed in theſe Methods, as they ſeem incorrigible, they muſt excuſe us if we cannot contribute our aſſiſtance to ſuch an Union as muſt terminate in our Ruin. The Laws have ever Eſteemed them, as well as the Papiſts, Enemies to the Peace of the Nation, and we know their Principles are inconſiſtent with the Ancient Conſtitution of the Monarchy, and both their paſt and late Actions have proved them true to their dangerous Principles, and the Character which Learned <hi>Grotius</hi> gives of them, That they ſubvert St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Rule of Subjection, and therefore that no Crowned head can be longer ſecure from their practices than while they want Power; and if Sedition, Rebellion, Murther, Rapine, Sacriledge, Uſurpation, Injuſtice, Oppreſſion, Tyranny, Cruelty, Perſecution exerciſed by Diſſenters du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their Empire, as is atteſted and avowed by their own Records, and juſtified in Print, be recommendatory Qualifications to truſt them again with our Lives, Liberties, Laws, Eſtates and Religion, judg all ye People!</p>
            <p>Nay, had they no other Crime beſides Ingratitude, I think that ſuch a Compendium of all that is ill, that they need not be painted more black than that has made them; and for that, let his Majeſties Gracious and Generous Act of Oblivion witneſs both their former Guilt, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Ingratitude: If they had not offended the Laws, and were not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to Juſtice, why did they ſtand trembling after his Majeſties wondrous Reſtauration till they got the Security of that Act? for which yet, the King out of the Abundant Excellency of his Nature, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exampled Clemency, ſeemed no leſs ſolicitous than the Criminals; and how they have requited his Royal Bounty, in all their late Actions, is an Ingratitude that not only <hi>England,</hi> but all <hi>Europe</hi> is with Aſtoniſhment a witneſs of.</p>
            <p>The King like a Juſt and Excellent Prince, who like Heavens Monarch delights in Mercy, ſuſpends the Rigors and Severities of the Penal Laws againſt them; this they conſtrue to be Fear and not Favour, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it to a confidence to demand their abolition, not without me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacing inſinuations upon refuſal: he aſſures them he will Govern ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Laws, to obviate a notorious Calumny ſpread abroad by them among his People of a Deſign of introducing Arbitrary Rule, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96141:3"/>that he will neither act Arbitrarily, nor permit others to do is; this is ſo far from giving ſatisfaction, that it is highly diſpleaſing; the Laws themſelves are Uneaſie, and to Govern by them burthenſom and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable; and indeed it is impoſſible to pleaſe thoſe with any thing, who are reſolute to receive no ſatisfaction unleſs they may have all.</p>
            <p>Whither theſe Procedures muſt lead us, we need not to conſult the Oracle. When the Quickſilver riſes ſo high in the Weather-glaſs of State, it is not difficult to conjecture ſome bluſtring may follow. And indeed the methods which theſe People have made uſe of, are too well known to leave us in ſuſpenſe, if Providence does not interpoſe, what will be the End: They have ſo far Exceeded the Limits of their Duty, and have ſo accuſtomed themſelves to affront the Government by the repeated breach of Laws, that it can be no wonder if they indeavour, even beyond what is conſiſtent with Loyalty, to be ſecured from the Penalties due to their diſobedience: and if they are ſo violent and head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrong when the Curb of the Law is ſo ſtrict upon them, can we ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally ſuppoſe they will be more tame and manageable, if they were ſecure of Impunity, or poſſeſſed of Power?</p>
            <p>The truth is, they are under the misfortune of all thoſe who having affronted Laws and Government, are perpetually haunted with their own Guilt, and the fear of Puniſhment; they can never think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſecure ſo long as there is a Superior Power to call them to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count: nor is any thing capable of obliging or giving them ſatisfaction, beſides an abſolute and unaccountable ſoveraignty.</p>
            <p>But how can this be Effected? God and Nature have veſted his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and the Laws of the Land have declared the Sole Power of the Sword to be his inherent Right, and it is both unnatural and irrational to ſuppoſe the Contrary; for without this he can neither Protect Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, nor Defend his Subjects: And though an <hi>Eſſex</hi> Addreſs was ſo confident to make a demand to have the Navy, Forts and Garriſons put into confiding hands, that is, into the Power of Diſſenting Proteſtants or their profeſſed Favourers; yet it is to be hoped that his Majeſty is too well acquainted, from the 12 Years Experience of his Exile during their Uſurpation, with their temper as to Loyalty, and too ſenſible who are his Enemies, from the many Diſturbances they have given him ſince his Happy Return, to truſt them with Power. A Scepter is a mere trifle without a Sword to guard it, and therefore there is little hope for them from that Quarter; nor can they have the leaſt ground to think that the King will ungird himſelf of his Royal Seignory, to oblige thoſe who will make no other uſe of it but to his diſadvantage.</p>
            <p>What? will they have a ruffle for it? truly, it has been confidently affirmed, That ſome of the Party who have wanted the gift of Tacitur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity have intimated as much; and the inſolence of their behaviour, the boaſts of their Numbers, though it is well known they make very falſe Muſters, and their Ten to One, is not One in Ten; together with the late Cavalcades of ſo many hundred Armed Men through the Streets of <hi>London,</hi> to attend ſome perſons towards <hi>Oxon,</hi> ſo directly contrary to the <hi>Statute</hi> of <hi>Northampton, 7 Edw.</hi> 1. and to the 2 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3. 20 <hi>R.</hi> 2.1. abſolutely prohibiting all Riding Armed to Parliaments, ſeemed to diſcerning men little leſs than a ſucking Rebellion, or at leaſt a Deſign
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96141:4"/>to awe their Sovereign into Compliance; and ſuch Extraordinary At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance contrary to Law, as it ſpeaks a guilt in the Perſons, ſo it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayes a fear on the one hand, and a confidence on the other never pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by any Subjects but ſuch who wanting the Guard of Loyalty and Innocence, fly to unlawful Arts and Arms for Safety and Protection.</p>
            <p>But Generous Countrymen, pray let us conſider of the matter a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle: Precipitation is the Daughter of Folly or Madneſs, and the Mother of Ruin and too late Repentance. I doubt not but all arts and inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations are uſed that may gain, encourage, animate or buoy up a Party, tis moſt evident every one ſees it, all perſons know it. Diſcontents are raiſed, Fears and Jealouſies ſuggeſted and blown up to the height, the People are debauched with falſe Repreſentations, and Rebellious Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and now that they are under a diſappointment, they are taught a certain Wild Enthuſiaſtick Faith, and by their Zealous Rabbies made believe that God has a great Work to do, that is, to deſtroy the Popiſh Church, of <hi>England,</hi> and work the thorough Reformation, and he will bring it to paſs though they cannot tell how; and thus their party are kept up in Expectation of ſome Miracles of Rebellion. This certainly is done in order to ſomething. And therefore it imports all <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> to conſider what they do, who they are managed by, what they may get or loſe; for certainly we of this Nation have ſomething to loſe beyond what all our Neighbours can boaſt of, but nothing to be got by altering our preſent Condition, and therefore by the moſt Early pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caution we ought to be aware of and indeavour to prevent any tenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to Rebellions or Inſurrections. I think Conſideration the Method of Sober and Judicious Men, and am aſſured no perſon ever loſt by thoſe moments ſpent in that Employ; but the want of it has ruined not only ſingle perſons and private Families, but Mighty States and Empires. I will therefore offer to your deliberating thought theſe following things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider who they are that make all this noiſe, and give theſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbances to the Nation? Upon Examination you will find they are thoſe very reſtleſs, murmuring Diſſenters, who within leſs than Forty Years with the ſame Acts turned the Kingdom upſide-down, turned the Monarchy, the Ancient Hereditary Imperial Monarchy of <hi>England</hi> into a Commonwealth or Republique, and who for that Reaſon and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Diſturbances they gave Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and King <hi>James,</hi> are by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny both New and Ancient <hi>Statutes</hi> of the Realm, deſervedly Eſteemed <hi>The Dangerous Enemies of the Government.</hi> Theſe are the Perſons that fill both the City and Country with Out-cryes of the Fears and Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of Popery and Arbitrary Government; who yet when they were got into the Throne of Uſurpation, acted by Popiſh Principle, and Popiſh Counſels, and the very worſt of the very worſt of Papiſts the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and of <hi>Jeſuits</hi> the moſt infamous, ſuch as <hi>Mariana</hi> and <hi>Scioppius,</hi> putting in Execution their Doctrines of Murdering and Depoſing lawful Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: who governed with the moſt Arbitrary Injuſtice imaginable; and notwithſtanding their Repeated Oaths and Promiſes to obſerve the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Laws, yet without Faith, Honour or Conſcience they Taxed, Aſſeſſed, Decimated, Fined, Impriſoned, Sequeſtred, Plundred, Baniſhed, and by a pretended High Court of Juſtice having thrown down the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96141:4"/>Supream Court of Judicature the Houſe of Peers as Uſeleſs and Dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, at their uncontrolled will and pleaſure, which was then theirs and our only Law, they Murdered whom they pleaſed, as the Reaſon of State to ſupport their Uſurpation made it appear Neceſſary or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient. Who to their Eternal Infamy put it three ſeveral times to the Vote, Whether they ſhould not give One Blow for all, and maſſacre all thoſe whoſe unſhaken Loyalty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Honour and Religion made them ſuſpect as Enemies; who kept up continual ſtanding Armies at a vaſt Expence, to maintain their unlawful authority, till at laſt the Servants turn'd out their Maſters, and made us all Slaves to the Law and Power of the Sword.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Perſons, or their Sons, for whom Diſſenters joyn all their Intereſts. For theſe <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> muſt be made Friends: nay ſome who were in the Black Liſt of the late King's Judges, and ſtrongly ſuſpected to have worn the Frocks and Vizzards, Excepted out of the Act of Indempnity, and the late General Pardon; ſuch who were in actual Arms againſt his preſent Majeſty or his Father, or the Sons of ſuch who having got Eſtates by the Rapines of the laſt Rebellion, and enjoy them by virtue of the Act of Oblivion; ſuch as have raiſed their inconſiderable Fortune, and Families, under the warm Sunſhine of Royal Bounty, and being waxen fat can kick againſt the Crown and ſpurn at the Mitre, and having gotten Thouſands by ſelling Places at Court, can call it <hi>the Houſe of Rimmon,</hi> and declaim againſt it, talk of Grievances, deny Money to Support <hi>Tangier</hi> or the Forreign Alliances, ſmile upon Diſſenters, and yet go to Church and hear the Publique Prayers, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sacrament, take any Oaths or Teſts to capacitate them for Places of Truſt and Power; and when they are in it, Exerciſe it to diſcourage and Oppreſs the Loyal, and animate the Factious; Theſe are the only perſons that are cryed up and cry up their own Abilities, Loyalty and Integrity, and muſt be the only perſons fit to repreſent the Country and ſerve the King.</p>
            <p>The Statute of 13 <hi>Car.</hi> 2.1. ſayes Expreſsly, <hi>That whoſoever ſhall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſedly publiſh or affirm the King to be a Heretick or a Papiſt, or that he indeavours to introduce Popery, or ſhall maliciouſly by Writing, Printing, Preaching or other Speaking, Expreſsly declare, publiſh or utter any words, ſentences or other things, to incite or ſtir up the People to hatred or diſlike of the Perſon of his Majeſty or the Eſtabliſhed Government, every ſuch perſon or perſons being thereof legally convicted, ſhall be diſabled to have or enjoy, and is thereby diſabled and made incapable of having, holding or exerciſing any Place, Office or Promotion Eccleſiaſtical Civil or Military, or any other Employment in Church or State, other then that of his Peerage, and be liable to ſuch other puniſhments as are inflicted by the Common Law. That ſuch as ſhall affirm by Writing, Printing, Publiſhing,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That the Parliament of</hi> Nov. 3. 1640. <hi>is not diſſolved, or that there lics any Obligation from the late Solemn League and Covenant or Engagement, or that both or either Houſe of Parliament hath a Legiſlative Power without the King, ſhall inour a Praemu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire as the Offenders againſt</hi> 16 R. 2. <hi>That a Peer or Commoner Convict of Offences againſt this Act, ſhall be diſabled during bit life to ſit in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, unleſs his Majeſty be gratiouſly pleaſed to pardon them.</hi> And though by a Proviſo there ſeems to be a reſerve for freedom of debate in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96141:5"/>yet what can be ſaid to thoſe Speeches Printed and Publiſhed, which tell us that we <hi>want a King and a Government whom we may truſt; That the Money given for</hi> Tangier <hi>may be made uſe of to raiſe an Army there. That diſcourſing of</hi> Tangier <hi>at this time, is like</hi> Nero<hi>'s Fidling whileſt</hi> Rome <hi>was conſuming by Fire.</hi> A very pretty compariſon to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Kings Meſſage; <hi>That a brand be ſet upon thoſe that adviſed the King not to paſs the Bill; That inſtead of looking into the</hi> Tower, <hi>they ſhould have looked into</hi> Whitehall, <hi>there the Plot is hatched, cheriſhed and brought up; That the Court is a Nurſery of Vice, and none but ſuch Men are imployed; That ſome Lords have little Eſtates, ſome little Conſciences, ſome leſs Religion;</hi> And all this printed by an Anabaptiſt, a very fit tool for a Reformation, if we would have one of the <hi>Munſter</hi> cut. Out of the ſame Shop comes the <hi>Vox Populi,</hi> and the Famous Addreſſes at Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which muſt be recorded <hi>in perpetuam Rei memoriam</hi> with the Title of <hi>Vox Patriae.</hi> We have ſeen Votes printed and publiſhed, and pleaded in Bar againſt the ſtanding unrepealed Laws in favour of Diſſenters; and if repealing Laws without the Kings Conſent, be not aſſuming a Legiſlative Power, what is? We have ſeen the Non-conformiſts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the notion of anſwering Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi>'s Sermon of the <hi>Miſchiefs of Separation,</hi> openly in Print avow the Obligation of the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant,</hi> pag. 13. <hi>There hath paſſed,</hi> ſay they, <hi>a Solemn Oath over the Nation, engaging the main Body of it to Endeavour a Reformation, and we dread to think on it with what faces they ſhall be able to ſtand before God, who have lift up their hands to him for things quite contrary in the late Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volutions.</hi> We have ſeen but t'other day a ſecond Character-man aſſert the Superiority of Parliaments to the Monarchy. <hi>Pag.</hi> 10. <hi>By which it is plain,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>That the Authority of the King being only Derivative, was inferior to the authority from whence it was derived, which was the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Which is a ſtep beyond the affirming a Legiſlative Power in the Two Houſes, which incurs a <hi>Praemunire,</hi> and is a plain veſting them with the Original of Imperial Sovereignty; and all this countenanced, promoted, and deliberately publiſhed to alienate the Affections of the People from his Majeſty, and preſented to them to ſtir up in them a diſlike of His Majeſties Perſon and the Eſtabliſhed Government. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all which, theſe muſt be the Hopeful Patriots and Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of our Liberty and Property; and we muſt not be Eſteemed true Proteſtants, unleſs we follow them in their Wild-gooſe Chaſe again, and with a pretended fear of Popery run into Anarchy, Confuſion, and every Evil work.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider, What muſt be the Way, and what the End, of theſe Violent Methods if they proceed to Extremities. The Sword is a Dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Umpire of our Differences; and yet this is the Arbitrator to which Rebels muſt flye, and with which Diſſenters ſeem to threaten us, if there be truth in their late Addreſſes, when they do with ſuch Oſtentation talk of aſſiſting thoſe that ſhall endeavour their ſatisfaction, with their Lives and Fortunes. And what muſt be the End of this? Know ye not that the Sword devoureth one as well as the other, and that it will be bitterneſs in the latter end? The Events of War are uncertain, but the Miſchiefs and the Miſeries certain. Let us therefore firſt ſit down and ſtate the account, compute our loſs and gain, and ſee what encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement we have for the Undertaking.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:96141:5"/>And firſt for the Proteſtant Diſſenters: Upon the firſt moment of an Inſurrection or Rebellion, the Gracious Act of Oblivion is gone; for though it pardons old Scores, it is not like one of the Popes Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which undertakes to pardon all the Crimes they ſhall do as long as they live; and if that be once Forfeited, their Lives, Liberties and Eſtates muſt be at the diſcretion of the Law, and the Mercy of the King, and he will have but little encouragement to oblige thoſe perſons with a ſecond <hi>Amneſtie,</hi> who have ſo much abuſed the Firſt; and however the more inconſiderable offenders may fall under the verge of Mercy as to their Lives, yet the principal Actors, Contrivers, and Managers of Rebellion can expect no more favour than the Juſtice of the Law will afford them, which is to be Drawn Hanged and Quartered, their Eſtates Confiſcate, their Families Ruin'd, their Honour loſt, their Names and Memories to be for ever Infamous, and their Poſterity to curſe them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, All their Liberties Franchiſes, Charters, Immunities, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, and even that great One of Chuſing and ſending Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives to Parliaments will be forfeited and loſt; for their Freedoms and Freeholds upon which that Priviledg depends, are by Rebellion <hi>ipſo facto</hi> loſt and gone.</p>
            <p>Nay, Thirdly, Should they prevail againſt the Government, which morally ſpeaking is impoſſible, their Circumſtances being ſo different from thoſe of the late Rebels, who had firſt diſarmed the Government before they attempted to overthrow it; Yet what could they rational<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hope for even after a Conqueſt? Is it poſſible for Men in their Senſes to imagine, that an Uſurping Power which is advanced by all the ſteps of Wickedneſs and the Violation of the Laws of God and Man, will va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue any Laws, Contracts, Oaths, Promiſes or Stipulations, or that they will not maintain a Standing Force to protect their ill acquired Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reignty? And if a Military Government be ſo Formidable in a Lawful King bounded by his own Laws, muſt it not be much more Dreadful in Lawleſs and Uſurping Tyrants? Was the Scepter of any Uſurpers ever made of any other metal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> than of Iron, or in reality any thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides a Sword? You know the Fable, The Horſe had a quarrel with the Stagg, and to ſatisfie his Ambition and Revenge, he takes the man upon his Back; 'Tis true he won the Field, but for ever loſt his Liberty, being unable to diſmount his Rider: Such Brutes are they, who being weary of their preſent Condition, ſet up a Power which reduces them to a worſe.</p>
            <p>Sovereignty and Supreme Power muſt be in ſome hand, there can be no Society, no Commerce, no living without it; and certainly it is moſt advantageouſly lodged there where God and Nature have placed it, and our Laws declared it to be; and the Reaſon is plain, We have not power to chooſe for our ſelves, for all Power is from God; and if we had, ſure 'tis an Atheiſtical preſumption to think we are able to make a better choice than the only Wiſe God: And beſides, what ſecurity can we poſſibly have from Uſurpers? Is it rational to think that they who can upon any conſiderations be tempted to violate their Faith and Allegiance to their Natural Liege Lord, ſhoul eſteem it a Crime to break their word with their Equals or Inferiors? it is juſt as likely as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96141:6"/>that he who thinks it no ſin to kill a man, ſhould ſcruple to tread upon a Worm. Remember how you were treated for Twelve Years after the Execrable Murther of the late King, and you will find I tell you the Truth and what is to be expected from theſe <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters,</hi> ſhould they get into Power, and become a Government by Rebellion.</p>
            <p>And becauſe there is a lamentable out-cry againſt <hi>Jus Divinum,</hi> and affirming Kings to Rule by Divine Right, and that therefore all Attempts or Rebellions againſt them are unlawful under what pretence ſoever, give me leave with a Digreſſion not wholly impertinent, to ſtop the mouths of theſe Ignorant or Deſigning Clamorers; They have often ridiculed Scripture Arguments upon that ſubject, and therefore I will offer them ſome Parliament Authorities, which ſeem to them far more convincing and Canonical. 1 <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 3. It is declared, That the Queen is, and ought to be by the Laws of God and by the Statutes of the Realm, our moſt Rightful and Lawful Sovereign Liege Lady and Queen; So that you ſee by Act of Parliament and a Proteſtant Parliament ſhe held her Crown, by this double Tenure <hi>Jure Divino &amp; humano.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 <hi>Jacob.</hi> 1. The King is Recognized to be Lawful Heir to the Imperial Crown of theſe Realms both by the Laws of God and Man; and this Act is Ordained to be a Memorial of Record by his Majeſties Aſſent to all Poſterity among the Records of the High Court of Parliament; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which Aſſent it could neither be compleat nor perfect, nor remain to all Poſterity. Theſe are the very words of the Statute; ſo that you ſee after all the noiſe which hath been made againſt <hi>Jus Divinum,</hi> the Title of our Kings is declared to be ſo by Two Acts of Parliament, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs thoſe words <hi>[The Law of God]</hi> have ſome other meaning which hitherto the great Maſters of Revelation have not diſcovered to us.</p>
            <p>But that I may come cloſe up to the Point, There is not that perſon in <hi>England,</hi> or any other of his Majeſties Dominions, of what Rank, Degree, Age, Sex or Condition ſoever, who has not beſides the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Concern a particular Intereſt which does oblige him or them to endeavour to maintain, defend, ſupport, and preſerve the preſent Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of the Government and Monarchy; and by clear conſequence, to deteſt, abhor, and by all Lawful wayes and means to labour to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, detect, oppoſe and prevent all ſuch Deſigns, whether of Papiſts or Commonwealth Proteſtants, who under Colour of Religion, Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, Liberty, Property, or any other of their ſpecious pretences ſhall go about to alter or ſubvert the proſent moſt Exeellent Eſtabliſhment. And to make this good, I will give a true but ſhort account of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Advantages which we do at preſent enjoy under his moſt Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Majeſty and the Monarchy; all which will be loſt or forfeited, if the Old Foundation be deſtroyed by Rebellion.</p>
            <p>I will begin with that which is in every mans mouth, and is every mans concern, the <hi>Magna Charea,</hi> or the Great Charter of <hi>England,</hi> the greateſt and moſt glorious Franchiſe and Immunity which is poſſeſſed by any Subjects on this ſide Heaven; This <hi>Charter,</hi> ſince the firſt Grant, has been confirmed above 30 ſeveral Times with all the dreadful ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities and imprecations upon whoever ſhould violate or infringe it; and if there were nothing in theſe formalities of its Ratification, yet the conſideration of ſuch an irreparable loſs, ought to make us jealous
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96141:6"/>and watchful againſt whatever may indanger it. Now though this Charter may be forfeited by Rebellion, and yet the Monarchy ſurvive, yet can it not poſſibly ſurvive the Monarchy, ſhould that be ſubverted or changed into a Common-wealth, as is evident both by the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and concluſion; for we hold it of the Kings of <hi>England</hi> and their Heirs; for ſo it runs, <hi>Henricus Dei gratia,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Know ye, That we have given and granted theſe Liberties following to be held in Our Kingdom of</hi> England <hi>for ever.</hi> By which it appears they are granted ſo long as it continues a Kingdom; and when ever it ceaſes to be a Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> or comes to be a Common-wealth of <hi>England,</hi> the Grant and Charter becomes null and void. And ſuitable to the Beginning is the Concluſion, which after the Enumeration of all the General and Particular Liberties and Priviledges, too long to be here inſerted, and too great to be loſt for want of due caution or conſideration, is in theſe words, <hi>Nos autem Donationes &amp; Conceſſiones praedictas ratas ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Which Grants and Conceſſions aforeſaid We having ratified, and being willing to ratifie for Us and Our Heirs, do grant, confirm, and renue by the Tenor of theſe Preſents, willing and granting for Us and Our Heirs, that this Our foreſaid Charter ſhall for ever be firmly and inviola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly obſerved in all and ſingular its Articles or Branches.</hi> By which it is evident, that it is the Kings Charter, that it depends upon the King and His Heirs; and being a Stipulation between the King and his Heirs on the one part, and the Subjects on the other, if one of the Parties ſhall ceaſe to be, the Grant, Charter, Conceſſion, and all its Dependencies ceaſe and fall of courſe, and are to all intents and purpoſes void and loſt for ever. And all the good Laws and Priviledges of King <hi>Egbert</hi> and King <hi>Aelfred,</hi> the great Monarchs of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Heptarchy, the Excellent Laws of <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor compiled out of the <hi>Britiſh, Saxon</hi> and <hi>Daniſh</hi> Laws, granted and confirmed by <hi>William</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror, which compoſe the Body of our Common and Statute Law, together with the Charter of the Foreſts, and indeed all our Laws, which are the Grants and Conceſſions of our Kings, and are therefore called the <hi>Kings Laws,</hi> muſt run the ſame Fate: And to what a deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable condition muſt that Nation be reduced, where the very Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Eſſence of Society, which is Government and Laws, are torn up, loſt, and ruined? Where the miſerable People muſt be left to the diſcretion and mercy of the Sword of Uſurpers to be governed arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, and be at their choice whether they ſhall enjoy any benefit or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage by their old Laws, and at the utmoſt uncertainty, whether they ſhall obtain new ones that will compenſate their loſs. A Wood which hath been many hundred years growing, may be cut down and reduced to Aſhes in a few days; but it is the work of Ages to re-plant it and make it flouriſh: and we have as little reaſon to believe, that what the Wiſdom and Induſtry of our Anceſtors hath been ſo many Ages oultivating, ſhould it be deſtroyed, can in a moment, or indeed for ever be repaired, as that Muſhromes ſhould advance to be Cedars, or Brambles grow up to be ſtately Oaks: Liberty is ſuch a Jewel, as being once loſt, rarely admits of the poſſibility of a Recovery, and therefore ſhould be kept with all the Caution imaginable. Our Laws are the true <hi>Argus,</hi> whoſe hundred Eyes are the Guards and Centinels
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96141:7"/>which watch againſt this Dragon of Rebellion which would devour it; and the Monarchy is the good Genius or Guardian-Angel of <hi>Great Britains</hi> Liberty; and ſhould we truſt it to the Devil of Rebellion, as once before, though clothed like an Angel of Light, we may flatter our ſelves with the Imaginations of a happy Change; but we ſhall find by woful experience, that our golden Liberty will be turned into Iron Fetters: and indeed when this great Bulwork of Liberty, our <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and the Foundations of our Laws, are either forfeited or uſurped by Rebellion, we muſt of neceſſity ſink into the utmoſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery and misfortune of ſervitude and ſlavery.</p>
            <p>I know this black and diſmal Reverſe of <hi>Englands</hi> Fate is induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly concealed from the People by the Common-wealth Proteſtants; and it would be unreaſonable to expect they ſhould ſhew us any thing that muſt of neceſſity pull off their Vizor, and by conſequence ruine the very hopes of ſucceeding in their Enterpriſe, which intirely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon their deceiving the People with Hopes and Promiſes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of Religion, Redreſs of Grievances, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> No, they treat us with theſe as Men do crafty Horſes, who being at eaſe and liberty in a full Paſture, are ſhie of being taken up and ridden; they ſhew us the tempting Provender, but conceal the Bridle which they have ready in the other Hand to ſlip over our Heads: They know when once they have put the Curb of Power into our Mouths, then the Arbitrary Saddle is ſoon clapt on, then the Riders may mount us at pleaſure, and what Loads they pleaſe may be laid upon our backs. We have ſeen and felt all this before, and therefore may with confidence aver it to be true: our Backs were galled and almoſt broken with the intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble burdens they laid upon us; our Sides ſtill remember the bleeding Marks and Laſhes of thoſe Hot-ſpur-proteſtants of the late Common-wealth of <hi>England,</hi> and the Keepers of our Liberties. We ſhould be very weak to expect it; but they muſt be worſe than Ideots, ſhould they tell us they deſign to Rebel or over-turn the Government. Did ever a Highway-man tell a Traveller that he intends to take his Purſe? No; he entertains him with the danger of the Roads, the great Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries that are done, and talks tragically againſt the Trade, pretends to be his Guard and his Conductor, tells him he will lead him ſuch by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, that he ſhall be ſure to eſcape them; and when he has once got him out of the Kings High-way, brought him into narrow Lanes among Woods, then he ſets upon him, robs, diſmounts, and it may be binds him, wounds or kills him. This is our Caſe, and when we ſee theſe Religious Padders, ſo buſie tickling the People in the Heads with dangers, fears and jealouſies, and drawing them out of the Kings High-way of Loyalty and Obedience into the Wood again, we muſt be inſenſible if we do not ſee what will be the End on't; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when we confider that both the Prologue and the Actors are the very ſame Perſons, or at leaſt of the ſame Principles, we muſt conclude they will act the very ſame Tragedy if they be not prevented.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, The King is the Fountain of Honour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Honour is both the Reward and Encouragement of Vertue; if the Fountain be dried up, the Streams muſt fail. The Duke, the Marqueſs, the Viſcount,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96141:7"/>Earl, Baron, Baronet; all hold by Patent, and flow from the ſource of Royal Bounty; and what becomes of all thoſe high Characters? If the Sun of Monarchy ſet, the Stats will fall and loſe their Luſtre, the Garter will be untied, and the Knights bright Spurs will ruſt; what will the Priviledge of Peerage, the <hi>Scandalum Magnatum</hi> fignifie, when <hi>Jack Straw,</hi> and <hi>Wat Tyler,</hi> a Dray-man, a Cobler, or a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier, ſhall be of more Authority than a Lord, nay than the whole Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Houſe, when it ſhall be voted uſeleſs and dangerous? The Peers are <hi>Pares Regns,</hi> Peers of the Realm; and if the Kingdom ſink or degenerate into a Democracy, or Oligarchy, the Honour of Peerage is gone, and the High and Mighty Princes may indeed have the empty Titles and Enſigns of Honour; but for any Authority, they muſt be reduced to the Common Level, and every little up-ſtart Favourite of the Uſurpers, ſhall not only venture at a Competition, but carry any Place of Power before them. This is no Fiction or Chymaera, but ſuch a Truth as Experience has within our Memory atteſted.</p>
            <p>And here with all due reſpects and difference I muſt addreſs my Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe to theſe Noble Perſons of the Delicate Sex; 'tis an ingrateful Complement to accoſt them with, to tell them their Honours will be loſt; but credit me; Illuſtrious Ladies, neither your Beauties, nor other moſt Attractive Charms, will be able to ſecure you from the Inſolence of Common-wealth Raviſhers: <hi>England</hi> can be no longer the Paradice of Women than it continues a Monarchy: My Lord can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſuffer, but my Lady will have a ſhare; the Widows of Barons, by the Curiality or Curteſie of <hi>England,</hi> enjoy the Titles and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Peerage, and the Daughters of Dukes, Earls, and Barons, do by the Favour of the ſame Cuſtom enjoy the Honour and Title of Ladies; theſe too muſt fall with the Monarchy; and in a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth <hi>Joan</hi> is as good as my Lady even by day-light. I remember <hi>Harry Martin,</hi> who was ſaid not to be the greateſt Enemy of the ſoft Sex, yet in the late times ſtretched a Commiſſion be had to ſeize Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for the Service of the Common-wealth, even to the taking the Coach-Horſes of ſome Noble Ladies ſitting the Parliament, which was an Inſolence and Breach of Priviledge; that, had Monarchy been in Power, he muſt have made a ſevere account for, but all the redreſs they could obtain, was to ſit down with the affront; for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Houſe juſtified him in it; and he juſtified himſelf for taking not only theirs but the Kings Horſes from the <hi>Muſe,</hi> by pleading this; We have, ſaid he, ſelzed the Kings Caſtles, Forts, Navy and Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zines; for the good of the Common-wealth, and ſure we may ſeize the Horſes of any Perſon for the ſame purpoſe: and the poor Ladies were obliged with patience to pocket up the Injury, and either ſtay at home, or learn to walk in Pattins, to make their Viſits, or take the Air, notwithſtanding their Quality, and the Priviledges of their Peerage.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The great Priviledge, the very Being and Eſſenne of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments falls with the Monarchy; for it is by vertue of the Kings Writ that Parliaments are called, choſen, meer, ſir, debate, and do every thing that a Parliament can do; without this there may be Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies or Conventions, but they are no more Parliaments than the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96141:8"/>Conſults of Jeſuits at <hi>Wild-houſe,</hi> or the White Horſe Tavern were Parliaments, and are in reality no better than Riots and unlawful Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, who have no Right, no Power, no Authority; and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they act or do, is a perfect Uſurpation and Arbitrary Invaſion of Sovereignty over their fellow Subjects: And what Juſtice, Equity, Law or Right are the People to expect from thoſe who can have no Power, all the People being their Equals? And when this ſhall once be underſtood, who will ſubmit to them or obey them who have no Authority to command, and then what Confuſions, Diſtractions, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrections, and Mutinies muſt follow, to the utter ruine and ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Peace, Trade, Juſtice, and the Proſperity of the Nation, till we come either to be a Prey to ſome Eorreign Invader, or ambitious Domeſtick Tyrant and Uſurper.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the Charter of <hi>London,</hi> the Imperial City, and thoſe large Liberties, Franchiſes, Immunities, Lands and Revenues, Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from Tolls in all places of <hi>England,</hi> nay their very Incorporation of Major, Aldermen, Common-Councel, Sheriffs, Courts, Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which are all the Favours of His Majeſty, and His Royal Progenitors, as at large appears by the Charter of <hi>London</hi> lately prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> muſt all ſtand and fall with the Monarchy from which they derive their Original, their Power, Authority and Juriſdiction, and without which they cannot ſubſiſt; and if Gratitude were not able (as I hope it will) to oblige this great Metropolis to a firm adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Crown, yet their Intereſt and Dependancy upon it does. For let us but conſider what a wild Deſert of unmanageable Brutes muſt this City of neceſſity be without Laws and Government, when even with the beſt and ſtrongeſt, which it enjoys under the Monarchy, together with the aſſiſtance of the Militia, all is little enough to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent diſorders, and hinder the licentious from ruining the Honeſt and Induſtrious: and ſhould the Indigent Multitude, the Licentious Rabble, and the Head-ſtrong and unconſidering Youth, come to know there was no Law to puniſh them, no Conſtables, Beedles, Juſtices, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pters or Officers, and Courts to reſtrain them, the Freemen disfran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſed, the Courts diſſolved, the Indentures of the Apprentices can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled, what could be expected but Riots, Tumults, Diſorders, and that the Rich and Wealthy ſhould become a Booty to the Poor, law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and unruly Multitude, and this now Well-governed, Rich, Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and Flouriſhing City become a Ruinous Heap, and have ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out upon it the Line of Confuſion, and the Stones of Emptineſs, and this great Mart or Emporium, famous throughout the Habitable World, loſe all her Trade, Riches, and Glory, and become the aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the whole Earth.</p>
            <p>Nor would the Leſſer Cities, Corporations and Burroughs be in a better Condition; all their Charters, Freedoms, Priviledges, Fairs, Markets, Tolls, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> being derived from the ſame Fountain of Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, muſt have the ſame Date and Period with it, to their utter Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing, Impoveriſhment and Ruine.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, All Priviledges granted to Merchants-Strangers, as the <hi>Hans</hi> Towns, the <hi>Lombard, Eaſtland, Norway, Spain; Venite, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy,</hi> the <hi>Dutch,</hi> &amp;c. and all our ancient and preſent Leagues of Peace,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96141:8"/>War, Offenſive and Defenſive, Commerce and Traffick made with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Princes and States are built upon the Foundation of the Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, and expire with it; and what a Damp muſt ſuch a Blow give to the Trade of <hi>England,</hi> when all the Forreign Merchants ſhall with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw their Effects for want of the Security of theſe Alliances; and how inſecure muſt our Merchants be without them, I leave to the Thoughts and Conſideration of thoſe Induſtrious and Worthy Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants who frequent the <hi>Change;</hi> which Place would have few Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants beſides the Statues of the Kings, who have encouraged, promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and advanced Commerce and Trade, if thoſe were permitted to ſtand, which I much queſtion; being they muſt reproach Uſurpers with Ingratitude and Diſloyalty. Forreign Trade is the great ſupport of <hi>England,</hi> and does ſo univerſally Influence all Mens Eſtates, that we ſee they riſe and fall in Proportion with the Actions of the Merchants; and what will become of the <hi>Eaſt India, Guinea, African, Turky, Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> Companies, and of all the Fraternities, Guilds and Companies of Trade in <hi>London,</hi> and all the Cities and Burroughs of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> whoſe very Eſſence and Being depends upon the Monarchy, and their Protection, Encouragement and Well being upon thoſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous Priviledges, Stipulations and Leagues of Commerce, which have been and are made with Forreign Princes and States, it is eaſie to determine: and ſhould any of our Potent Neighbours, upon our unhappy Circumſtances, ingroſs the Trade, and turn the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of it, let <hi>Antwerp</hi> teach <hi>London,</hi> and <hi>Flanders England,</hi> that Staples and Factories, once removed, are difficultly, if ever, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gained.</p>
            <p>Beſides that, the ſetting up a Common-wealth, as it Cancels our Leagues and Alliances, ſo it muſt put us into a ſtate of War with all our Neighbours; for all Crowned Heads muſt of neceſſity, in regard of the dangerous Precedent and Example ſuch a Revolution gives their Subjects, be declared Enemies; and for Republicks, the Emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation that is between them can never permit them to be Friends.</p>
            <p>Sixthly. Nor will the Diſmal Effects of changing the preſent Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Government only affect the Nobility and the Merchant, the Gentleman muſt have his ſhare too; for whereas there are about 10000 Mannors in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> whereof the Lords are as it were little Kings among their Tenants, and have the Liberties of <hi>Sake, Soke, &amp;c.</hi> and many Juriſdictions, as Court-Barons, Court-Leets, to order and do Juſtice to their Tenants, from whence ariſe Fines, Amerciaments, Eſtreats, Forfeitures, Deodands, Waifs, Strayes, Fines certain and incertain, Quit-rents, Heriots, Freewarren, Swanning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all theſe being Grants of ſeveral Kings, have their dependancy upon, and muſt run the ſame Fate with Monarchy, if that ſtands, they ſtand, if that falls, they muſt fall alſo, to the no ſmall loſs and detriment of all thoſe Noblemen, Gentlemen, Bodies-Corporate, and others, who are at the preſent poſſeſſed of them.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, And leſt there ſhould be any Perſons to whom the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs of Rebellion will not extend, its Conſequences will affect the Body of the Commons, the Free-holders, Copy-holders, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon People, there being none who have any thing to loſe, but muſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96141:9"/>hazard and loſe all, and many Thouſands their Lives in to the Bargain: it will ſtrip the Copy-holders, which are above a fourth part of the Lands of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> of all their Ancient and Beneficial Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, the Common People of their Rights, Apportionments and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaſurement of Common of Paſture, Common of Eſtover, Agiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in Foreſts and Purlieus, which in many Places of <hi>England</hi> are the greateſt part of the Livelihood of the Inhabitants, all which they poſſeſs by vertue of the Grants and Charters of ſeveral Kings; and for the Free-holders, when their Intereſt in <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Repreſentatives are gone, they will have little left to boaſt of.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, Nor will it only wrong the Living, but the Dead; for not to mention the Impropriations and Advowſons to Rectories, which depend upon Grants from the Crown, what will become of the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of Colledges in the Univerſities, Free-ſchools, Hoſpitals, Almſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, all which poſſeſs their Revenues by Charters and Grants from the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> and depend upon the Monarchy; and ſhould that fall (which God forbid) their Titles are gone, and they muſt be at the Will of the New Lords, who according to the Proverb, will be for new Laws. And how near the Brink of Ruine, and being ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the devouring Avarice of Pretended Religion, all theſe Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations and Supports of Learning were in the late Rebellion, need not be remembred, ſince it is impoſſible it ſhould be forgotten; and ſince among our Proteſtant Diſſenters, the Compter, the Cart and the Plough can afford ſuch plenty of Learned Apoſtles, Evangeliſts, Elders, and Teachers, there will not want a <hi>Judas</hi> to cry out againſt Univerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Tithes, <hi>Quorſum perditis haec?</hi> Why all this loſs? let them be ſold to maintain the Charges of the Common-wealth. Thus it was, and thus it would be again, if they had Power, which I confeſs gives me ſome admiration to ſee Perſons who pretend to be learned and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourers of Learning herd with ſuch illiterate and ignorant Impoſtors. How were the poor People cajoled with taking away the burden of Tithes, as they called them in the late times; whereas had they been taken from the Clergy, whom they would render poor and mercenary, that they may not have courage to oppoſe Rebellion; yet the poor Laicks would have had no more benefit than the Aſſe, whoſe wiſe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, to eaſe him, took off the Load which before he rid upon, and laid it upon his own ſhoulders; which though it loaded him, did not at all lighten his Brother Animal.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, Neither will it ſtop here, but paſs the Seas, and diſcharter all the Forreign Plantations of <hi>Virginia, Maryland, Carolina,</hi> &amp;c. which are holden by the Proprietors by vertue of Royal Grants.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, To conclude, it will render the whole Nation Slaves: for I pray once diveſt us of the before recited Charters, Freedoms, Immunities and Liberties, either by the prevailing of Uſurping Rebels, or by the forfeiture of Rebellion; and what are we but the moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicable and abject Slaves? and of all ſlavery that is certainly the moſt inſupportable, where we muſt ſubmit to the Yoak of our Equals and Inferiors.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:96141:9"/>Thus have I given you, Generous Countrymen, a ſhort but true Character of that Monſter Rebellion; which though ſhe puts on the Face and Voice of an Angel, always hath the Hands of a Devil. If you have any remainders of true <hi>Engliſh</hi> Courage and Gallantry, for which your Anceſtors have been ſo renowned; if you think Liberty and Property worth the preſerving, either to your ſelves, or to be tranſmitted to your Poſterity, it imports you to uſe your utmoſt indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to cruſh the Cockatrice of a Common-wealth in the Egge, and by all lawful ways and means to ſupport, maintain, and defend the Monarchy with the laſt drop of your Blood, and the laſt Penny of your Eſtate: It is your indiſpenſable Duty, the Laws of God, and the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of the Realm require it, your own ſafety, preſervation, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed your whole Intereſt challenges it from you; it is a Juſtice to your Poſterity, to whom you were better leave no Name, than the infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Intail of ſlavery to their Fellow-Subjects, Manacles and Chains inſtead of Charters and Royal Franchiſes; which as they have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended to you, you ought to take care to tranſmit them to Poſterity whole and entire.</p>
            <p>I know the greateſt Criminals will make the firſt and loudeſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations of Innocence and Loyalty: Who ſo brisk as <hi>Hazael</hi> to repar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee to the weeping Prophet, who charged him with the Barbarous Miſchiefs he would do when he ſhould get into Power; what am I a Dog that I ſhould do this? Who ſo quick as <hi>Judas</hi> to put the Queſtion, Is it I? But we have learnt to read Men by their Actions, not their Words; and that I may not criminate without Proof, which is Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny and Detraction, I refer you to the Teſtimony of two Evidences that will not deceive, and can neither be accuſed of detracting Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice or biaſſed Partiality; the one is Law, the other is Old Experience: By theſe you ſhall know who are the Enemies of the Monarchy and eſtabliſhed Government.</p>
            <p>Now the Law expreſly charges Papiſts and Sectaries, or Diſſenting Proteſtants, with the Accuſation of being dangerous Enemies to the Government. That the Papiſts are ſo is allowed of all hands; and that the other are no more innocent in the Eye of the Law, is evident, in that there is not one Title of Law, the leaſt ſhreds of Records, which can give them a favourable word; but on the contrary, 35 <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 1. charges them with the danger of great inconveniences and perils which may happen and grow by the wicked and dangerous Practiſes of Seditious Sectaries; and the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt turned this into a Propheſie, which they fulfilled; 13 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1. charges the Growth and Encreaſe of the late Troubles upon their ſcore; and we know it was they that preached us into Rebellion, and fought us into ſlavery; and the 13 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1. tells us, All His Majeſties Endeavours and unparallel'd Indulgence in pardoning all that is paſt has not been able to oblige them, but that nevertheleſs many evil Spirits are ſtill working; and therefore for prevention of miſchief for the time to come, and for Preſervation of the publick Peace both in Church and State, be it Enacted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This we have found true ever ſince. 16 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 4. tells us of growing and dangerous Practiſes of Seditious Sectaries, and other diſloyal Perſons, who under pretence of tender
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96141:10"/>Conſciences, do at their Meetings contrive Inſurrections, as late Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience hath ſhewed. 17 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2. informs, that they diſtil the poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonous Principles of Schiſm and Rebellion into the Hearts of His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Subjects, to the great danger of the Church and Kingdom; ſo that the Teſtimony of the Laws and Statutes of the Realm are clear againſt them, and declare them dangerous Enemies: and if there were nothing elſe, their ſtrict Confederacy in the Common Cauſe, and the ſudden Reconciliation that is among ſo many differing Sects who are mortal Enemies in perſwaſion, and damn one another as deep as Hell, only to get the Penal Laws againſt them repealed, is a ſufficient acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement from themſelves, both what our Laws eſteem them, and what they eſteem our Government; and truly one of them ſpeaks plain, <hi>Plotters Doom Pag.</hi> 10. where he tells you, <hi>That if</hi> Martin Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>were alive, he would call thoſe,</hi> who put the Penal Laws in Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt Proteſtant Diſſenters, <hi>the Devils Magiſtrates, and the Devils Miniſters, and not Gods,</hi> and a little after, <hi>Of theſe therefore beware as of the Devil, whoſe firſt begotten Children they are.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And leſt the ſingle Teſtimony of the Laws ſhould not be ſufficient, Experience makes good the Charge; have they not been infamous for Sedition, Conſpiracies, Rebellion? Have they not actually once before overthrown the Monarchy, ſet up Arbitrary Power, trampled under foot our <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> Liberty, Property, Lives and Religion, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered their Lawful Prince, Baniſhed his Son? and had not Providence miraculouſly interpoſed, nothing could have ſecured us from utter Ruin and Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Nor will it at all avail them now to pretend that they abhor and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt all ſuch Deſigns or Intentions; the ſaving their Necks and Eſtates oblige them to that Declaration, and the Deſign they have to impoſe upon the People, keeps that concealed from them; but yet they are not ſo cautious at all times, nor ſo full of abhorring, all the Art of Man cannot perſwade them to abhor their <hi>Dagon</hi> of the Solemn League and Covenant, or to abhor the Traiterous Poſition of taking up Arms by His Majeſties Authority againſt His Perſon; which if they did not think Rebellion Lawful, or did not intend to Rebel upon a fair occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, they would voluntarily and <hi>ex animo</hi> declare to be their Senſe and Judgment.</p>
            <p>But that you may ſee through theſe thin Pretences to Loyalty, Duty, and Affection to His Majeſty, pray obſerve, firſt that the Late Rebels did the very ſame; who ſo Dutiful and Loyal, ſuch faithful Subjects as the Diſſenting Proteſtants, till they had graſped the Power, and when Victory, which they argued was a Declaration of Gods Favour, had Elevated their Arms, then the Note was changed, and he who before was treated with the Stile of Sovereign and Majeſty, could get no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Language from them than plain <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> Tyrant and Uſurper, and after the loſs of His Crown and Life, to have His Reputation mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered with an Epitaph in Capital Letters, written under the Pedeſtal, from whence they had pulled His Statue in the Old Exchange, <hi>Exit Tyrannus Regum Ultimus,</hi> that there might be as many Nations Witneſſes of their Infamous Villany, as Curioſity or Commerce draws to that Publick Place; which for my Particular, I cannot but look upon as
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:96141:10"/>an infatuation in them, that forced them to proclaim their own Infamy and Guilt to the whole World, and that there ſhould ſcarcely be a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion under Heaven that is not able to produce a Teſtimony againſt them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Obſerve, That the Survivors of that Black Tragedy have not given one ſingle Symptom of Repentance for their former Guilt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but as a moſt Infallible Demonſtration, that they are given up to the utmoſt Impenitence, and a ſeared Conſcience; notwithſtanding all their Pretences to Tenderneſs, they do not only continue obſtinately in their Errors, but compaſs Sea and Land to proſelyte others to their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions; and it is evident it is not Religion, but Deſign, that is the chief Motive that gives fire to their Zeal, that they are for the Drag-Net of a Toleration, and all are Fiſh that come to the Net, if they do but center in the main Point which unites all theſe true Proteſtants, which is to oppoſe the Government. How do they upon all occaſions either exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate or endeavour to evade the Horrid Crimes of which they were the Actors; do they not, as before was inſtanced, notwithſtanding the Premunire they incur, ſtill adhere to the Covenant? Are not all the Conventicles ſhut up on the 30th of <hi>Jan.</hi> leſt they ſhould ſhew any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe for their having ſhed the Blood of the Juſt, and call themſelves Villains by deploring the Tragedy wherein they were principal Actors, Abetters, and open Juſtifiers? Have they not conſtantly oppoſed the Government both in Church and State, broken the Laws, diſturbed the Peace, and do they not avow and juſtifie their doing it with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Conſcience? and if they be the ſame Perſons as they ſhew plainly they are, if ever they were dangerous, they are ſo ſtill, and their pleading Not Guilty is no more Juſtification againſt the Teſtimony of the Laws and Experience, than it is in any other Criminals and Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Obſerve, They do exactly trace the ſame Method and Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of the late Rebellion; they begin with Popery, but they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently change the Scent, and fall upon Prelacy, the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the Loyal Party. Theſe muſt be hunted down for Papiſts, Tories, Tantivies, Penſioners, Evil Counſellors, and Enemies to the King and Kingdom, and thoſe muſt have the Title of the only true Proteſtants, who are the moſt fierce and violent Schiſmaticks, and ſuch as favour them, muſt be reputed the only fit Perſons to repreſent the Nation; whilſt ſuch Loyal Gentlemen or their Sons, who hazarded their Lives and Fortunes in defence of the King and Government, are contemned, affron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, puniſhed, and treated with all the ignominious and reproachful Terms and Marks of Infamy that ſpite and artful Malice can invent to render them odious or ſuſpitious to the People: They traduce the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and endeavour to make it contemptible, revile the Biſhops, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lign the Loyal Peers, vilifie the King, and have much to do to keep from down-right Treaſon; and if theſe be not ſufficient Arguments to prove that they are Enemies ſtill, dangerous Enemies to the Monarchy, our Ancient Laws, Government, Eſtabliſhed Religion, and to the true Intereſt and Happineſs of <hi>England,</hi> I think if an Angel came from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven he would not find credit; for ſure I am he might manage it with greater skill, but he could not produce more demonſtrative Truth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:96141:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>This, my Generous Countrymen, is the true ſtate of your Intereſt, and our preſent Affairs: This is what you muſt expect, ſhould theſe Zealots come to give you Laws: If therefore you have any value for your ſelves, your Poſterity, your Liberties, Property, Laws, the true Proteſtant Religion, the Trade, Peace, or Honour of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it is both your Intereſt, and your Duty, to aſſert and ſtand up for the Monarchy, to ſupport the Laws and Government to the uttermoſt of your power, and by all Lawful Ways and Means to convince, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade and reclaim the Credulous and Miſtaken, to ſuppreſs, oppoſe, and defeat the Deſigns of theſe Factious dangerous Sectaries and Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks, for ſo our Laws call them, who with fair Speeches, and flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Pretences, ſteal the Hearts of the People like <hi>Abſalom,</hi> only to exalt themſelves into Sovereign Power, and reduce you to the deſperate Condition of ſlavery, which is always the Reward and Iſſue of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:96141:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
